<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reasonablenesse of wise and holy truth: and the absurditie of foolish and wicked errour</title>
            <author>Terry, John, 1555?-1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13629</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23912</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118354</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853561</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853561</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18948</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13629)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18948)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1223:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reasonablenesse of wise and holy truth: and the absurditie of foolish and wicked errour</title>
                  <author>Terry, John, 1555?-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 38, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Lichfield, and William Wrench, printers to the famous Vniversitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: John Terry.</note>
                  <note>A sermon.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Title page mutilated, affecting imprint; title page through p. 7 from Bodleian Library copy filmed at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18948:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18948:1"/>
            <p>THE REASONA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLENESSE OF WISE AND holy truth: and the abſurditie <hi>of fooliſh and wicked Errour.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>ECCL. 7. 27.</bibl>
            <q>I haue compaſſed about, both I and mine heart, to knowe and to enquire, and to ſearch wiſdome and reaſon, and to knowe the wickedneſſe of folly, and the fooliſhneſſe of madneſſe.</q>
            <bibl>MATTH. 11. 19.</bibl>
            <q>But wiſdome is iuſtified of all her children.</q>
            <figure>
               <p>AC: OX</p>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD</hi> Printed by Iohn Lichfield, and William Wrench Printers to the famous Vniverſitie. 161<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18948:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18948:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God, ARTHVR, Lord Biſhop of BATH and WELLES, Vice chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of the Vniverſitie of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and Warden of <hi>New Colledge,</hi> IOHN TERRY wiſheth all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of that Glory and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, wherevnto you are <hi>called by our moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious &amp; holy Lord.</hi> 2. Pet. 1. 2.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y duety bindeth me (right Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and my very Good Lord) to offer vp to God for you the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of thankeſgiuing and prayer. Some of the Heathen of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred ſacrifice to the ſunne riſing for benefits to come: and other to the Sunne ſetting for ſuch as were already receaued. VVherefore it being a great ſhame for a Chriſtian to be out gone in any good dutie by an Heathen, I cannot but offer vp to our moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sauiour Chriſt the true Sonne of righteouſneſse, the ſacrifice of thankſgiuing: first, for cauſing ſuch a bright ſtarre as your Lordſhip is to appeare aboue our Horizon in the weſt: and ſecondly for cauſing you to ſet with leauing much good to that Colledge, whereof my ſelfe was once a member. And how can I alſo but
<pb facs="tcp:18948:3"/> offer vp prayer to God; firſt, that the freſh memorie of your renowned learning and religious life may inſtill ſuch a ſweet influence of celeſtiall grace into the hearts of all the members of that ſocietie, that they may bee effectually ſtirred vp to walke in your waies, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote themſelues by your example to the publike good: as ſecondly I am to beſeech him that walketh in the midſt of the ſeauen golden Candleſticks, and holdeth the ſtarres in his right hand, that he would hold &amp; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold you long to his owne glory, and to the edification and comfort of his people, among whom hee hath now placed you to hold out the word of life. And thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending you to God the Father of light, and to the word of his grace the moſt worthie instrument thereof, with all humble thanks vnto your Lordſhip for your louing acceptance of this ſmall paper preſent, I reſt</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips in all Chriſtian loue and dutie, JOHN TERRY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18948:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>IOHN. 17. 17.</bibl>
               <q>Sanctifie them with thy truth: thy word is truth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Chapter containeth a moſt divine and heavenly prayer of our moſt bleſſed Saviour Chriſt wherein hee requeſteth of his Father, that hee would by the gracious word of his Goſpell, make more and more manifeſt the glorious worke of mans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. For that hereby he and his father ſhould be moſt glorified, and all ſuch as his father had giuen him, ſhould be made partakers of life everlaſting. For <hi>this is everlaſting life</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to know thee the only true God, and whom thou haſt ſent</hi> (videlicet, to accompliſh the worke of the redemption of all the elect) <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> For the cleere doctrine of the Goſpell, laying open the glorious worke of mans redemption, doth make ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the light of Gods countenance ſhining in Chriſt, and doth giue vnto all that are truely lightned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, the holy eie of ſauing faith, whereby they aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly apprehending, and moſt certainely beleeuing the vnſpeakable loue of God towards them that do cleaue vnto Chriſt, and are made one with him, and by him haue communion and fellowſhip with God; and ſo are made partakers of life everlaſting. And verily the true ſauing faith wrought by the Goſpell, is nothing elſe but ſuch a ſure and certaine knowledge of Gods vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable loue in Chriſt, as is accompanied with all
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18948:4"/> manner of holy and heavenly graces. And therefore as v. 8. our Saviour teſtifieth that he had given his Fathers words to them, which he had giuen vnto him, and they had receaued them, and had ſurely knowne that hee came from the Father, &amp; had beleeued that the Father had ſent him: ſo in this verſe hee prayeth to his Father that the would ſanctifie them with the truth that was contained in the ſame word. In the which petition of our Saviour Chriſt, we are to obſerue theſe two points firſt, the thing that our Saviour requeſteth at his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hands; that hee would beſtow vpon all thoſe that he had giuen him, which is, Sanctification: Secondly, the meanes whereby it is wrought, which is the truth of his owne word. <hi>Sanctifie them with thy truth: thy word is truth.</hi> Now the ſanctification that our Saviour here prayeth for, is not maymed, wanting any eſſential part, but totall and whole; even ſuch a ſanctification, as doth ſanctifie the minde with ſauing knowledge, &amp; faith, the will, and the affections, with all other graces, and gifts of the holy Ghoſt, and ſo doth ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the whole man. Neither is this whole and total ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification beſtowed onely vpon ſome principall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Church of Chriſt, but even vpon the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt alſo. As the Apoſtle teſtifieth 2. Cor. 3. 18. <hi>Wee all</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>behold as in a mirrour the glory of God with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen face,</hi> there is the ſubiection, action, obiect, &amp; clere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of faith) <hi>and are changed into the ſame image from glory to glory, as by the ſpirit of the Lord</hi> (there is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable effect of ſauing and ſanctifying faith, one and the ſame in ſubſtance, though not in circumſtance in all the faithfull.) And verily, how can it otherwiſe bee, but that all ſuch as <hi>by faith are engraffed into Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 11. 17. ſhould immediatly be made good trees, &amp; ſo conſequently be enabled to <hi>beare good fruit.</hi> Mat. 7.17. How can it otherwiſe be, but that all ſuch as by the <hi>linely word of God,</hi> Heb. 4. 12. <hi>are quickned to a liuing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18948:4"/> faith.</hi> Gal. 2. 20 <hi>ſhould ſhew themſelues to be aliue to God</hi> Rom. 6. 11. by the exerciſe of al holy and godly works. For nature is never idle, much leſſe grace. Gal. 5. 6. and therefore, <hi>as the body without the</hi> (operatiue) <hi>ſpirit is dead: ſo faith without workes is dead alſo,</hi> Iac. 3 26. And therefore the ſame Apoſtle in the ſame chapter willeth <note place="margin">Natura eſt nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam otioſa.</note> all ſuch as lay claime to a true faith, to make proofe thereof by their good workes, after the example of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham the father of the faithfull. For after that he had ſhewed himſelfe readie at the commandment of God, to offer vp in ſacrifice his moſt deare ſonne Iſaac, then he made it manifeſt that he ſo firmely apprehended by an aſſured faith, the incomprehenſible loue of God in Chriſt, Eph. 3. 19. towards himſelfe, that he preſerred it before his moſt intire loue towards his own moſt deare ſonne: and then was the Scripture fulfilled: <hi>Abraham beleeued God, and it was imputed to him for righteouſnes.</hi> Wherefore it was not without cauſe that S. Peter wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to ſuch as had obtained like pretious faith with himſelfe, willeth them to ioine to their <hi>faith vertue, to vertue, knowledge; to knowledge, temperance; to te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, patience; to patience, godlines; to godlines, brotherly kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; to brotherly kindneſſe, loue,</hi> 2. Pet. 1. 5. For (ſaith he) if faith want knowledge, it is a blind credulity, and not a cleere eie wherewith we ſee God, &amp; heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, albeit it be a farre off. v. 9. And if it bee not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with all theſe divine graces, it is an idle &amp; fruitleſſe fancie, verſ. 8. and not a true working and fruitfull faith. Gal. 5. 6. But if it bee accompanied with theſe divine graces, then it proueth it ſufficiently, to be the faith of Gods elect. Tit. 1. 1. and aſſureth al ſuch as are indued therewith, that they are effectually called to the eſtate of grace, and are elected to everlaſting life. verſ. 10. And verily, even by the light of nature it is recorded that the Graces goe hand in hand, and will in no wiſe part company: and by the light of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18948:5"/> it is further iuſtified, that they are as a moſt pretious and golden chaine, Ez. 16. 11. the linkes whereof can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſevered. How then can a true faith being one of the principall vertues that are by Chriſt infuled into the hearts of all true Chriſtians, Eph. 6. 16. Ioh. 6. 19. be ſevered from the ſocietie of the reſidue of the divine graces of the ſpirit of God? Doth not the Apoſtle plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly avouch, that <hi>wee are all the ſonnes of God by faith in Chriſt.</hi> Gal. 3. 26. Ioh. 1. 12. and therefore renued into his image in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe? Are wee not <hi>by faith vnited vnto Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 3. 17. <hi>and at one with God?</hi> Rom. 5. 1. How then can it be a neare compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with blindneſſe and ignorance, or with vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and ſinne? For <hi>what communion can there be betweene light and darkneſſe? what concord betweene righteouſneſſe and vnrighteouſneſſe?</hi> 2. Cor. 6. 14. But there is ſo great an agreement betweene faith and loue and the reſidue of the divine graces of the ſpirit of God that S. Auſtin doth place them in the definition of faith, as if they were the very eſſence thereof. For, <hi>what is it</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to beleeue in God, but to loue God, and to loue God?</hi> that is, to loue God with a double loue. Aug. in Ioh. tr. 29. So. in Pſ. 77. To beleeue in God, is to cleaue to God, &amp; to worke that which is good together with him that worketh good in vs. Wherefore let all ſuch as make profeſſion, that by faith they ioyfully imbrace the covenant of mercy in Chriſt, and yet are careleſſe in the performance of all holy duties, nay, which turne the grace of God into wantonneſſe, Iac. 4. and vpon a preſumptuous opinion of the infinitie of the mercy of God, and merits of Chriſt, doe looſe the raines to all manner of wicked and corrupt affections. Let them all knowe that <hi>howſoeuer in word they make profeſſion of the faith of Chriſt, yet in their deeds they denie the ſame.</hi> Tit. 1. 16. For how doth he ſay that he beleeueth in Chriſt, who doth not that which he commandeth him to doe?
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18948:5"/> 
               <hi>Cyp, de ſimpl. praelat.</hi> How then can hee that doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that which God commandeth, ſay that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth in Chriſt, and is partaker of the covenant of grace? For vnto the vngodly, ſaith God, <hi>VVhat haſt thou to doe to declare mine ordinances, and to take my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in thy mouth?</hi> Pſ. 50. 16. So Ier. 7. 9. Will yee ſteale, murder, commit adulterie, &amp; ſweare falſely, &amp;c. and come and ſtand before me in this houſe whereon my name is called, as if yee were my ſeruants, whereas yee cloth your ſelues with the Divels livery, and doe ſuch works as belong to his ſervice? Will yee ſay that yee are deliuered from the ſlauerie of ſinne, &amp; yet pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute your ſelues with all maner of abominations? <hi>How ſhall we</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that are dead to ſinne liue any longer therein?</hi> Rom. 6. 2. Surely if Chriſts death doth deliuer vs from the guilt of our ſinnes, it will firſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver vs from the dominion of our ſinnes: and if Chriſts reſurrection ſhall raiſe vs vp to be partakers of eternall life, it will firſt raiſe vs vp to <hi>newneſſe of life.</hi> 1. Cor. 25. 34. Apoc. 20. 6. For vndoubtedly a wiſe and an holy faith, whereby <hi>we liue to God,</hi> Gal. 2. 20. muſt go before our glorification, &amp; iuſtification alſo. For whom God electeth in Chriſt before all worlds, to thoſe by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and effectuall calling, he giueth a wiſe and an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faith, whereby they are made <hi>the ſonnes of God,</hi> Gal. 3. 26 &amp; are renued vnto his image in righteouſnes, &amp; true holines, that ſo reſembling their heauenly father, hee may take them for his owne deare children. Now whom he thus calleth, them he iuſtefieth (for by faith we muſt be firſt engraffed into Chriſt, before wee can haue intereſt in his righteouſneſſe, whereby wee are iuſtified) and then, <hi>them whom he iuſtifieth, he alſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth.</hi> Rom. 8. 30. A ſanctifying faith is then the firſt of all the proper and peculiar gifts that God beſtoweth vpon all thoſe to whom he vouchſafeth to giue an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable place in his houſe and family. 1. Cor. 6. 11.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18948:6"/> Tit. 3. 5. 6. 7 &amp; a greater alſo then iuſtification it ſelfe. For it is a greater bleſſing to be delivered from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and bondage of ſinne, then from the guilt and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment thereof: for that the one is a farre greater e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill then the other. The making of an impious a iuſt man (as Thomas A quinas teacheth) is the greateſt of all the workes of God. So S. Auſtin writing vpon theſe words of our Sauiour Chriſt (<hi>greater workes then theſe ſhall they doe</hi>) ſaith that it is a greater worke of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious man to make a iuſt man, then to create heauen &amp; earth. Aug in Ioh. tract. 72. For in the creating of all things of nothing, as there was nothing to further, ſo there was nothing to hinder the work: ſeeing nothing hath no activitie, but in the recreation or regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of man, there is not onely no furtherance in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural <note place="margin">Non ent is nullae ſunt qualitates.</note> man, but a great hinderance &amp; reſiſtance. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not without cauſe that the faithfull, recording in what danger they were by reaſon of their ſinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their regeneration and ſanctification, doe greatly reioice and ſay: <hi>The right hand of the Lord hath ſhewed forth his mightie power; the right hand of the Lord hath advanced me.</hi> Aug. confeſ. l. 4. c. 3. Wherefore ſeeing an holy faith, which is accompanied with all the reſidue of the graces of ſanctification is the greateſt of all the peculiar gifts of God, even ſuch an one, as whereby we haue not only <hi>an entrance into the eſtate of grace,</hi> Rom. 5. 2. but are preſerved there by to eternall ſalvation. 1. Pet. 1. 5. wee ought to imploy our firſt and our chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt care for the obtaining and preſeruing of the ſame. And that ſo much the more, for that not only God is principally ſerued, and glorified, and our ſelues beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefied thereby. Ioh. 6. 29. but alſo that ſo we may ſtop the mouthes of our adverſaries. For among al the moſt ſlanderous imputations that they lay to our charge, this is not the leaſt, that they avouch that wee teach a bare and naked faith, without the fruit of all good
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18948:6"/> workes, in that wee affirme that faith is alone in the worke of our iuſtification. The which is as true, as if they ſhould ſay, that wee hold that the eye is alone in the body without the reſidue of the other ſenſes, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that wee avouch that the eie is alone in the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of all ſuch things as are ſubiect vnto ſight. And yet for this cauſe we muſt be called <hi>Sol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fidians</hi> as if wee reiected all other fruits of the ſpirit with the practiſe &amp; exerciſe of all good works. Nay, let vs make no leſſe vſe hereof, then Philip did of thoſe ſlanders, the which the Athenians had raiſed vp againſt him: I am much (ſaid he) beholding to the Athenians, for that by their ſlanderous reports I am made the more careful to look to my waies, that I may hold a right courſe, that ſo I may confute them, both by my words and workes. So likewiſe, whereas our doctrine is, that the true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſaith is accompanied with all manner of divine and heauenly graces, and is fruitfull in all good workes, let vs giue all diligence to confirme the ſame by an holy life and converſation, that ſo we may confute them by our deeds alſo. And ſo we may bee bold to retort vpon them iuſtly and truly, that which they vntruely charge vs withall. For in that they avouch that the true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith, may not only be in the reprobate, but even in the very divels themſelues, thereby they teach that it may be alone without the company of any vertue, &amp; without the practiſe of any good worke. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they may be truely tearmed not onely <hi>Solifidians,</hi> but <hi>Implijfidians,</hi> &amp; <hi>'Diabolifidians</hi> alſo. Vndoubtedly hereby they make it manifeſt to the whole world, that they hold not the true Catholike faith, ſeeing thereby in the iudgement of S. Auſtine, the iuſt are diſcerned from the vniuſt. Aug. ad Bomf. l. 3. c. 5. Whereas by that faith which themſelues hold to be Catholike, they cannot be diſcerned from the very Divels themſelues. Now if they bee not ſevered from the Divels in their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18948:7"/> faith, neither can they bee ſeuered from them in their workes, ſeeing faith is the root, &amp; works are the fruits; and ſuch a root, ſuch a fruit: Now if they bee ſevered from the Divell neither in their faith nor workes, how can they bee ſevered from him in their puniſhments? Wherefore let them diſgrace this gracious gift of faith which haue no part nor portion in the reward thereof, But as for vs which acknowledge it to be a principall part of true ſanctitie and holineſſe: let vs moſt careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerue the meanes whereby it is coliated, by God ſet downe in theſe words of our text: <hi>Sanctifie them with thy truth: thy word is truth.</hi> Wherein we are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue theſe two points: Firſt, that God doth ſanctifie his by the truth: ſecondly that this truth is contained in Gods word, even in that word of God which is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered vnto vs by the Prophets and Apoſtles. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the firſt, which is, that truth is the true meanes whereby we attaine to an holy faith, and to all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of the graces of ſanctification, it is manifeſt in this, that truth doth rectifie our vnderſtanding, will, &amp; affections: in the vprightneſſe of the which, our whole and totall ſanctification doth conſiſt. And therefore by S. Auſtine, truth is tearmed, <hi>The virginitie of the ſoule, and the chaſtitie of the mind,</hi> As falſehood, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth is the adulterous pollution of them all: inſomuch that all ſuch as in Gods ſervice embrace lyes either ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by tradition from their anceſtors, or ſucken out of their owne heads, are iuſtly charged by the ſpirit of God <hi>to goe a whoring after humane inventions.</hi> Num. 15. 39. Here of it is that men of al profeſſions lay claime to the truth, and for proofe thereof make a ſhew to deriue the pedegree of their doctrine from God the author of truth, and from his word the authenticall, and vndeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able evidences thereof. As it may appeare by Celſus. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Who as Origen reporteth, entituled his bookes, <hi>The word of truth,</hi> which yet hee wrot againſt the truth.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18948:7"/> Wherefore as the Apoſtle exhorteth, we are not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue every ſpirit, but to trie the ſpirits whether they are of God or no: and wiſely to examine the grounds of all doctrines, before that we make them Articles of our Creed: that ſo we may imbrace the knowledge of the truth, whereby we may bee ſaved, and reiect the ſtrong deluſion of Satans lies, which are the venome and poiſon of our ſoules. 2. Theſſ. 2. 10. Now the word of God which our bleſſed Saviour, the wiſdome of God Prov. 8. revealed by his ſpirit to the Prophets and Apoſtles, is this word of ſanctifying and ſauing truth. For if we continue in the ſame, <hi>We ſhall knowe the truth, &amp; the truth ſhall make vs free.</hi> Ioh. 8. 32. And how doth truth make vs free, but by ſanctifying vs with al divlne and heavenly vertues? For a true vertuous man is the only free man.</p>
            <p>Let vs then come to the ſecond point, and take a true view of ſuch proofes as may be produced, to make manifeſt, that the word of Chriſt revealed by his ſpirit to the Prophets and Apoſtles, is only the rich treaſury of that pretious truth, whereby all the elect of God are brought to a ſanctifying and ſauing faith. The which thing that we may effect, let vs firſt ſearch and enquire where and what truth is, that ſo truth may ſpeake and manifeſt it ſelfe. Truth is either in things or words. Truth in things, is the fit and apt agreement of the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes with their effects, and the effects with their cauſes, of the accidents with their ſubiects, and ſubiects with their accidents: and ſo of all other arguments and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, with the things whereof they are argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. <note place="margin">Vera eſt propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitio qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatum conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit ſubiecto. Tum praedicatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>venit ſubiecto cum eſt genus. &amp;c.</note> So truth in words, is when true reaſons which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the things whereof they are reaſons, are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly ſet downe in the words, which are deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to expreſſe the ſame. Hence then we thus conclude that if all true reaſons whereby the true God and true Godlineſſe may be knowne and embraced, are rightly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18948:8"/> ſet downe in the doctrine revealed by Chriſt to the <note place="margin">Tum veritas eſt in verbis quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ita eſt in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus quemadmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum verb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant.</note> Prophets and Apoſtles, and by them regiſtred, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled in the Canonicall Scriptures of the old and new Teſtament: then this word is the word of God, and the word of truth. But in theſe bookes are ſet downe all manner of moſt forcible and effectuall arguments, and reaſons for the rooting vp of all errors and vntruths, &amp; for the opening &amp; confirming of all doctrines of faith, and godlineſſe, and for the edifying of the ſpirituall <note place="margin">Scriptura eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons rationalis.</note> temple of God. Let vs (ſaith S. Hierome) aſcend into the reaſonable mount, and ſeeking of the teſtimonies of Scripture choice and fit timber for every ſeverall point of doctrine: let vs cut it downe, and there with build the houſe of wiſdome. Hier. in Hagg. Neither doth this word of God miniſter choice timber onely for the building vp of the Lords Temple, but all maner of wholſome food alſo for the ſuſtenance of all ſuch as are of the Lords houſhold. For in it there is both <hi>milk</hi> for children, &amp; <hi>ſtrong meat</hi> for ſuch as are men. Heb. 5 12. The principles of this word, are the childrens milke: which is by S. Peter called a doctrine, ſtanding <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> vpon ſo ſure and ſound reaſon, that hee that rightly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth the ſame cannot bee deceaued. 1. Pet. 2. 2. whereby he doth diſtinguiſh it from the principles of <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. <hi>Pet. 1. 16.</hi>
               </note> all other religions, which being not Logicall but So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſticall, as happely hauing in them a ſhew, but not the ſubſtance of ſound reaſon, cannot but deceaue and deſtroy all ſuch as drinke downe the venomous poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thereof. Now if the firſt rudiments of the word of God ſtand vpon ſuch ſound reaſon that they cannot deceaue, then the ſtronger meat thereof, which is all ſuch reaſons and arguments which are ſet downe for the further lightning and ſtrengthning of theſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, muſt needs bee of greater light and ſtrength. And ſo no doubt they are: ſeeing they are of power to make the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God which are long exerciſed therein
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18948:8"/> able ſo throughly to diſcerne betweene good &amp; evill, errour and truth, that they can both purely and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly performe vnto the Lord that <hi>reaſonable ſervice</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which is acceptable vnto him, Rom, 12. 1. The which reaſonable ſervice, what is it elſe but the puritie of a true ſaith, and of all oather divine vertues, with all holy workes that iſſue from them all? Ioh. 6. 29. 1. Tim. 6. 11. Now <hi>faith</hi> (as the Apoſtle defineth it, Heb. 11. 1.) <hi>is the ground of things hoped for, &amp; the demonſtration of things not ſeene:</hi> which principally are the vnſpeakable loue, and goodneſſe of God demonſtrated, not onely in the worke of the creation. Rom. 1. 20. but eſpecially in the worke of the redemption. 2. Cor. 3. 12. For this is ſuch a demonſtration of Gods vnſpeakable goodneſſe and loue, that (as Auſtine ſaith) it doth convince the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and after a ſort force the minde to yeeld her aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thereto. Aug. in Ioh. hom. 79. &amp; 95. <hi>So God loued the world</hi> (ſaith out bleſſed Saviour) <hi>that he gaue his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten Sonne, that whoſoever beleeueth in him ſhould not periſh, but haue life everlaſting.</hi> Ioh. 3. 16. So Saint Iohn. <hi>In this appeared the loue of God towards vs, in that God ſent his only begotten ſonne into the world that wee might liue through him.</hi> Ioh. 4. 9. And againe, <hi>Herein is loue, not that we loued God, but that God loued vs, &amp; gaue his Sonne to be an attonement for our ſinnes.</hi> And againe, in the very next verſe, <hi>If God ſo loued vs, &amp;c.</hi> As if hee would haue vs throughly to vnderſtand, that ſuch a perſon giuen for ſuch perſons to worke ſuch a worke, is ſuch a demonſtration of Gods loue, that the like is no where to be found, no not in all the Bookes of Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotles Demonſtrations. When I was here a ſcholler, I heard a moſt reverend Father, namely M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Fox, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching on theſe words of the Apoſtle: <hi>If one bee dead for all, then we were all dead.</hi> 2. Cor. 5. 14. ſay here is ſuch an <hi>ergo,</hi> that all the Schooles cannot ſhew the like. And yet this <hi>ergo</hi> &amp; demonſtration whereof we now ſpeake
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18948:9"/> is a more forceable <hi>ergo,</hi> &amp; a more compelling demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, as the ſame Apoſtle teacheth in the former part of the ſame verſe. For verily if we could attaine <hi>to all riches of the full aſſurance of vnderſtanding, to knowe the myſtery of God even the Father, and of Chriſt.</hi> Col. 2. 2. Then we ſhould attaine to the <hi>full aſſurance of faith,</hi> Heb. 10. 22. even to the full aſſurance of Gods loue. If wee were able <hi>to comprehend with all Saints, what is the breadth, length, depth, and height of the loue of Chriſt that paſſeth knowledge,</hi> then ſhould <hi>wee bee filled with all fulneſſe of God.</hi> Eph. 3. 18. In the meane ſeaſon, all ſuch as haue attained to ſome meaſure of this faith, which is grounded vpon ſo ſtrong demonſtration, are called by S. Chryſoſtome. hom 9. in Epiſt. ad Coll. <hi>ſheepe indued with reaſon,</hi> for that they are, or ſhould bee able to giue <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> anſwer to every one that asketh them a reaſon of the hope that is in them. 1. Pet. 3. 15, And verily all ſuch Chriſtians as rightly vnderſtand the grounds of their faith are eſteemed by the Apoſtle to bee worthie of the name of reaſonable men: whereas all that doe not, are by him branded with the note of men wicked and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable. Furthermore (ſaith he) bretheren pray for vs, that the word of the Lord may haue a full current, &amp; be glorified, as it is with you, and that we may be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from vnreaſonable and evill men: for <hi>all men haue not faith.</hi> 2. Th. 3. 1. Neither is this firſt and principall part of Gods ſeruice only grounded vpon moſt ſure &amp; ſound reaſon, but alſo the other part thereof conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the exerciſe of all holy works, proceeding from al the divine graces and gifts of the holy ſpirit of God. For if they be not done after that manner, and by the inducement of ſuch reaſons, as God in his word re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth <note place="margin">Deus non exige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat quae ſiebant ſed propter quod fiebant. Tert. 1, 3 cont. Marc.</note> them to be performed, they are not allowed, and approued of Chriſt. Mat. 6. 1. 1. Cor. 13. 1. For that may bee ſaid of all good workes which Tertullian a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voucheth of the Iewes ſacrifices: Viz: that God did
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18948:9"/> not in them require the thing done, but the reaſons for the which they were to be done: ſo God doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire our bare workes, but will haue them done vpon ſuch reaſons and motiues as they ought to be done. So then the very rudiments and principles of this word of Chriſt are reaſonable milke: &amp; the ſervice therein pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, is a reaſonable ſervice: and the faith therein commanded is grounded vpon a moſt ſtrong demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration: and the workes therein required are ſquared by the ſquier of exact reaſon: and the perſons that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace this faith, are only and alone eſteemed to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with right reaſon: therefore we rightly conclude that this word of Chriſt ſet downe in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Prophets &amp; Apoſtles is the only vnerring word of truth. And verily, vnleſſe the holy Scriptures were furniſhed with all varietie of arguments and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to convince all errors, and to confirme all truths, how could the profeſſors of the Chriſtian faith be ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled thereby, to convert or confound all heatheniſh perſons, and all heretickes and ſchiſmatikes, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and ſtrengthen the faithfull themſelues? For if we will deale with Ethnikes, we muſt not produce the bare teſtimonies of the Prophets and Apoſtles as of witneſſes immediatly inſtructed &amp; ſent into the world by God, to giue an vndeniable evidence to truth: (for that were to begge that as granted, which is by them not only queſtioned, but alſo peremptorily denied) but they muſt be dealt withall by arguments and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as being a plea allowed by all as are, or thinke themſelues to be indued with right reaſon. And among the great varietie of arguments and reaſons, where by all queſtions are handled, and diſcourſed of, wee muſt not at the leaſt principally vſe ſuch of them as moſt prevaile with the affections and will; but rather ſuch as doe inſtruct the vnderſtanding and the minde. For (as Tertullian ſaith) <hi>Truth perſwadeth by teaching:</hi> that <note place="margin">veritas d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuadet.</note>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:18948:10"/> is, it teacheth the vnderſtanding, &amp; ſo prevaileth with <note place="margin">Falſitas ſuaden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do docet.</note> the affections and will. Whereas, <hi>Falſehood doth teach by perſwading:</hi> that is, perſwadeth the affection &amp; will, and ſo moueth the mind to aſſent vnto error. The truth of both which poſitions is verified by the experience of all ages. For what prevaileth moſt with the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons but the enſamples of our Ancients, cuſtome, a good intent, and an outward peace and plentie of all temporall bleſſings? And haue not theſe beene vſed as principall arguments by Schiſmarikes, Heretikes, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, and Ethnikes? <hi>Our Fathers</hi> (ſaid the ſchiſmatical Samaritans) <hi>worſhipped in this mount.</hi> Ioh. 4. 20. I haue ſo receaued from my Progenitors (was the plea of that infamous heretike Eutiches) In this faith was I borne and conſecrated to God, and in this I deſire to die. Concil. Chalced. act. 1. So Dioſcorus in the ſame place, I doe find the doctrine of the ancient Fathers not cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorily deliuered, but handled of ſet purpoſe in their bookes: I am reiected with them. So the Idolatrous Iewes ſaid that they would doe whatſoever went out of their owne mouthes; as to burne incenſe to the Queene of heauen, and to powre out drinke offerings to her: as they had done both they and their fathers, their Kings and Princes in the cities of Iudah, &amp; in the ſtreets of leruſalem: for then (ſaid they) <hi>they had plentie of victuals, and were well, and felt no evill.</hi> Ier. 44. 17. So the hereticall and idolatrous Papiſts cry out both ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally for the Fathers, the Fathers, the Church, the Church, Antiquitie, Vnity, Vniverſalitie; &amp; particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto his Maieſtie, your holy progenitors, your deare mother were profeſſours of our Romane religion. Laſtly, ſo the old Idolatrous Ethnikes: <hi>That which is more ancient cannot be falſe. Aug. de Civ. Dei. l.</hi> 39. But how did the ancient Fathers themſelues reply herevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? <hi>What wilt thou doe</hi> (quoth Lactantius writing in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Chriſtian faith) <hi>againſt the Idolatrous Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nikes?
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18948:10"/> wilt thou follow thine Anceſtors, or reaſon rather? Lact. de vero Dei ſimulachro. cap.</hi> 20. So Cyprian <hi>ep, 7. cent: Quint, We are not to preſcribe by cuſtome, but to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince with reaſon.</hi> So Tertullian: <hi>We are not to eſteeme of faith by the perſons, but of the perſons by the faith.</hi> Yea this kind of reaſoning, reaſon it ſelfe hath taught, even the naturall wiſe men. I am thus reſolued (ſaid Plato in <note place="margin">Nullius addic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus iurare in verba magiſtri.</note> Critone) not now but alwaies, that I am not to enthral my iudgement vnto any of my freinds, but to reaſon: yea to that reaſon which by diſcord appeareth to bee beſt. Whoſe opinion was ſeconded by the chiefeſt of all his ſchollers. <hi>Plato is my friend, but truth is more my friend. Arist. Mor. l. 1. c.</hi> 3. For the efficacy of reaſon is better then all authorities. <hi>Zalm. in c. 5. ep. ad.</hi> Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe why doe all learned men of all profeſſions call for a generall diſputation, that they may iuſtifie all their poſitions by logicall ſyllogiſmes. Yea why doth God himſelfe call the Idolatrous Ethnikes, ſtanding in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their heatheniſh Gods, to this manner &amp; kind of triall? as Iſa. 41. 21. 22. 23. <hi>Stand to your cauſe, ſaith the Lord, bring forth your ſtrong reaſons, ſaith the God of Iacob. Let them bring them forth, and let them tell vs what ſhall come: let them ſhew the former things what they be, that wee may conſider them, and knowe the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of them: either declare vs things to come. Shew the things that are to come hereafter, that wee may knowe that yee are Gods.. Yea, doe good, or doe evill, that we may declare and behold it together.</hi> In which wordes are ſet downe two reaſons, whereby the true God may be diſcerned: whereof the one is the doing good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill. The other, the declaring of things paſt, and of things to come. And verily the true God is goodneſſe it ſelfe, and hath declared himſelfe to be ſo by the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the world, and by communicating ſome porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his owne goodneſſe to every creature therein. And therefore, as Pythagoras ſaid, if any beſides one
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18948:11"/> God ſay, I am God: let them ſhew a world like to this, and ſay thereof, this is mine. For the creation of this one world is ſo ſure an evidence to proue that there is but one God, that this one God willeth his people to ſay to the Ethnikes that ſhall ſtand in defence of their Idoll Gods: <hi>The Gods that made not the heavens &amp; the earth ſhall periſh from the earth, and from vnder the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi> Ier. 10. 11. <hi>And verily the Gods of the heathen are but Idols: for it is the Lord that made the heavens.</hi> Pſal. 96. 5. Now if the heatheniſh Gods ſhall aſſume to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the glory of this great worke of the creation, then ſaith the Lord in the place before alleaged, <hi>Let them ſhew it to be ſo, either by revealing things paſſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of the world, or things that are to come to paſſe even to the end.</hi> For vndoubtedly, <hi>knowne vnto God are all his owne workes from the beginning of the world.</hi> Act. 15. 18. and as certainely hee knoweth what ſhall become of them to the end, yea what ſhall come to paſſe for ever and ever. As it is vndoubtedly true, that the heatheniſh Gods cannot tell what ſhall come to paſſe in time to come concerning ſuch things as are to be effected by ſuch cauſes as are ſet on worke by their owne wills: and therefore are no true Gods. For if it be replyed that the Prieſts and Prophets of their heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Gods haue declared ſuch things before hand: as namely their Propheteſſes called <hi>Sybillae,</hi> haue ſet down ſome as diſtinct particulars concerning our Saviour Chriſt, and the works of redemption wrought by him, as were foretold by Moſes and the Prophets: wee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that as Plato did <hi>Moizare,</hi> that is, deliver many doctrines ſet downe by Moſes for that hee had taken them out of him: So theſe Sybille did <hi>Prophetizare,</hi> becauſe they had receaued theſe propheſies either out of their books, or by tradition from the old Patriarks. For as Sampſon ſaid vnto his gueſts that were at his wedding, when they gaue him the right ſenſe of his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18948:11"/> riddle which lie had propoſed vnto them: <hi>If yee had not plowed with my heifer, yee could not haue found out my riddle.</hi> Iud. 14. 18. So may wee as truely ſay, that if the heatheniſh Prophets and Propheteſſes had not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted with our Prophets, they could not haue delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red theſe Oracles. The which is evident by this, that when they were conſulted by their greateſt friends concerning events that were preſently to come to paſſe, they deliuered their Oracles in doubtfull ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which might be expounded divers waies, for that they were not able to deliver any certaintie thereof. As; <hi>Aio te Aeacides Romanos vincere poſſe.</hi> And <hi>Craeſus halim penetrans magnam pervertet opum vim.</hi> Whereas our Prophets not only delivered the certaintie of the events of divers battles when they were ready to bee vndertaken. as Iud. 4. 9. and 7. 9. 1. Sam. 30. 8. 1. Reg. 20 13. But alſo many other events many hundred yeares before they fell out. As namely the deliverance of the Iewes out of the captivitie of Babylon, and the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular king by whom it ſhould bee accompliſhed, even Cyrus king of the Medes &amp; Perſians. Iſa. 44. &amp; 45. The which propheſie, as Ioſephus reporteth, <hi>Antiq. Iudaic. l. 11. c.</hi> 1. Cyrus reading and perceauing himſelfe to be named therein ſome 200 yeares before he was borne, and appointed to ſuch a worke, gaue liberty to the Iewes to returne to their-owne country, and to build their temple, and he gaue them backe the veſſels there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which had beene carried away by the king of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. For he vnderſtood that the God of the Iewes was the true God, becauſe he had foretold ſuch an event a long time before it was to come to paſſe. As it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by his owne words, Ez. 1. 2. <hi>Thus ſaith Cyrus King of Perſia, the Lord God of heauen hath given me all the kingdomes of the earth, and hath commanded mee to build him an houſe in Ieruſalem which is in Iudah. Who is among you of all his people with whom his God is? Let him
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18948:12"/> goe vp to Ieruſalem which is in Iudah, and build the houſe of the Lord God of Iſraell: he is the God which is in Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi> Here then wee may perceaue by evident reaſon ſet downe in the Scriptures, that the heathen haue and therefore ſtill may be convinced to acknowledge him to be the true God, who hath revealed himſelfe in thoſe bookes of the Prophets and Apoſtles, and that thoſe bookes are the authenticall word of the true, all ſeeing and well working God. And verily even the moſt profoundeſt myſteries of thoſe bookes may bee iuſtified by evident reaſon to the heathen themſelues to be the doctrines of truth proceeding from the true God: as it may appeare by the bookes of theſe notable lights in the Church of Chriſt. <hi>'D. de Pleſſis de veritate Chriſtianae religionis. Zeged. in locis com. Keckerm. in Syntagm. Theolog.</hi> Neither muſt the doctrines of our Chriſtian religion bee by reaſon evicted againſt the Gentiles, but alſo againſt all Schiſmatiks, &amp; Heretiks. For albeit all theſe, or at the leaſt the moſt of them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the holy Scriptures to proceed from God, yet ſeeing this word of God conſiſteth not in the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters but in the ſence, not in the reading, but in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, not in the leaues of the ſpeech wherein it is delivered, but in the root of the reaſon whereon it is grounded: and ſeeing all Schiſmatikes and Heretikes, be the words that are produced againſt them never ſo plaine and pregnant, yet peruert and corrupt the right ſenſe and meaning of them, how can the right ſenſe be iuſtified againſt all ſuch perſons, but by cleere and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent reaſons? For if one teſtimonie bee produced to cleere another, they will pervert the ſenſe of the one as well as of the other. And if the teſtimonies of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers, yea of generall Councels bee alleaged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, either they will pervert the meaning of them aſwell as they did the meaning of the Scriptures, or elſe they will flatly refuſe to ſubſcribe to their auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18948:12"/> The truth hereof was fully knowne vnto S. Auſtin, who for his learned confuting of many heretikes, was called the <hi>Hammer</hi> wherewith heretikes were knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">Malleus haere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum.</note> in the head. For hee writing againſt Maximinus the Arrian. l. 3. 1. 14. ſaith; I will not alleage the Councell of Nice to preiudice thee, neither ſhalt thou produce the Councell of Ariminum to preiudice me: I will not be bound to yeeld to the autority of the one, nor thou to the authority of the other: but by the autoritie of the Scriptures, as by moſt indifferent witneſſes, not proper to either of vs, but common to both. Let matter with matter, cauſe with cauſe, reaſon with reaſon, bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared together, &amp; let that prevaile which is the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and weigh moſt wherein there is the moſt weight. And verily there is no other meanes to cleere the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of all teſtimonies, humane, and divine, then by the light of cleere arguments, and reaſons. Wherefore ſeeing that the power of the word of God conſiſteth in the right ſenſe and meaning thereof, which cannot be cleered without the light of reaſon, &amp; without the ſure apprehenſion thereof, the people of God them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues cannot be edified; therefore cleere arguments and reaſons muſt bee produced for the cleering of all doctrines of faith, and an holy life by all ſuch teachers as ſeeke after the edification of the people of God. The truth whereof is plainely confirmed by the vſuall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of all preachers of the word of God. Among who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is moſt ordinary, after the doctrines deduced out of their texts, to cleere the ſame with varietie of reaſons, and then to drawe out the vſes there of, which are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but particular doctrines by evidence of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon collected and gathered out of the generall. And verily the true Chriſtian faith is not an ignorant credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, but an vnderſtanding aſſent grounded vpon a ſure knowledge: even ſuch a faith as was in the Apoſtles themſelues, &amp; the which they were to preach through
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18948:13"/> out the whole world. Luk. 1. 77. For of this their faith, our Sauiour himſelfe teſtifieth in this very chapter, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>I haue giuen them the words which thou gaueſt mee, and they haue receaued them, &amp; haue knowne ſurely that I came out from thee, and haue beleeued that thou haſt ſent me.</hi> v. 8. The truth where of is plainly confirmed by <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the words of S. Peter. Ioh. 6. 69. <hi>Thou haſt the wordes of eternall life: &amp; we beleeue &amp; knowe that thou art the very Chriſt the ſonne of the liuing God.</hi> Neither is this vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding faith proper and peculiar to the teachers of the truth, but to all the godly profeſſors of the ſame. For <hi>none come to ſalvation but by the knowledge of the truth.</hi> 2. Th. 2. 10. 11. In which place knowledge and faith are ioined together as inſeparable companions: as Ignorance is ſet downe as a ſeparatiſt from faith &amp; ſalvation in the former chapter of the ſame Epiſtle. Now to knowe a thing is to knowe the reaſons there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <note place="margin">Scire eſt per cau ſas ſcire.</note> Wherefore the true Chriſtian faith grounded vpon knowledge, doth no otherwiſe worke in the faithfull a right aſſent to the ſeverall doctrines of faith then by grounds thereof. This truth is manifeſtly proued throughout the whole body of the ſacred Scripture, which teacheth that the true Chriſtian faith is a wiſe, and holy, not fooliſh and wicked, a ſeeing and not a blind; a cleere and not a darke; a manly and not a chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh; a reaſonable and not a brutiſh perſwaſion. Faith is a wiſe aſſent grounded vpon the wiſe doctrines of the word of God, <hi>which are able to make vs wiſe to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by faith in Chriſt.</hi> 2. Tim. 3. 15. And what is wiſdome but a right apprehenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of truth &amp; the reaſons thereof by the teſtimonies of divine &amp; humane autors? <hi>I haue</hi> (ſaith Solomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wiſe) <hi>compaſſed about both I &amp; mine heart to knowe and inquire and to ſearch wiſdome, &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> Eccl. 7. 27. by the which manner of annexing the one to the other, hee giueth vs to vnderſtand that the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18948:13"/> one ariſeth out of the other. So Ariſtole, the wiſeſt of all Philoſophers. <hi>Prudence is an habit ioyned with right reaſon.</hi> So Tully one of the wiſeſt of all Orators: <hi>Hee that doth beſt apprehend truth in every thing, &amp; the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and grounds thereof is worthely to bee esteemed the moſt prudent and wiſe of all other.</hi> Wherefore our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith being a wiſe apprehenſion, and aſſent vnto truth, muſt needs apprehend the reaſons whereon it is grounded. <hi>The wiſdome of the prudent</hi> (ſaith Solomon) <hi>is to vnderſtand his way: but the fooliſhneſſe of fooles is deceit.</hi> Prov. 14. 8. That is; wiſdome lightning the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding by meanes of true reaſon, doth ſanctifie it with truth: as folly darkning it with ignorance, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it into errour both in matters of faith, and of life, and converſation. For <hi>the fooliſhneſſe of a man pervert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his waie,</hi> Prov. 19. 3. <hi>for folly is the mother of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> Eccl. 7. 27. Wherefore, <hi>ſuch as bee fooliſh ſhall not ſtand in Gods ſight: for he hateth all ſuch as worke wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> Pſ. 5. 5. <hi>But the wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſſe of the firmament.</hi> Dan. 12. 3. The fooliſh Virgins could not enter into the marriage becauſe their lamps were gone out. Mat. 25. 10. That is, they made profeſſion of the word of God, which is a lanthorne to our feet, and a light to our paths without the vnderſtanding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For what is the word not vnderſtood, but a lampe without oile, or a candle without light? But the wiſe that had oile in their lamps, that is rightly vnderſtood, the doctrines of Gods word were admitted into the marriage. For they that truely knowe God, ſhall bee <note place="margin">Viſio iustificans Viſio glorificans</note> knowne of him: and they that now ſee him with the eye that iuſtifieth, ſhall hereafter ſee him with the eye that glorifieth. But they that knowe not God, ſhall not be knowne of God, 2. Theſſ. 1. 8. Hoſ. 4. 6. Prov. 1 22. And all ſuch as ſee him not with the eye of faith, ſhall never ſee him with the eye of glory. Prov. 29. Fooles &amp; mad men may be Saints with fooliſh and mad Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18948:14"/> but <hi>the children of wiſdome</hi> Mat. 11. 19 are the chil dren of the moſt wiſe God: &amp; ſuch as haue their minds and affections ſanctified by wiſdome, are his Saints, <hi>in whom are hid all the treaſures of wiſdome and knowledge.</hi> Coll. 2. 3. Now if faith be a wiſe aſſent, then it is not blind and darke, but eyefull and cleere. <hi>I ſaw</hi> (ſaith So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon the wiſe) <hi>that there is more profit in wiſdome the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in folly, as the light is more excellent then darkneſſe.</hi> Eccl. 2. 13. for <hi>a wiſe mans eyes are in his head, but a foole wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in darkneſſe.</hi> Wiſdome and faith are the ſight of the eye of the mind: and truth rightly apprehended and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto, is the light that leadeth in the' right way <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Morio</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>quaſi</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> vnto God. Pſ 43. 3. But a foole &amp; vnbeleeuer <hi>is a blind and a darke man.</hi> 2. Pet. 1. 9. For infidelitie and folly is the blindneſſe of the mind: and where theſe lead the will and affections, there is a wandring from God (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>he that walketh in darkneſſe, woteth not whether hee goeth.</hi> Ioh. 12. 35.) and there is a falling into the pit of all errors and ſinnes: ſeeing where the blind lead the blind both fall into the ditch. Wherefore, bleſſed are their eies who ſeeing ſee, and doe perceaue, &amp; hearing heare, and doe vnderſtand, and ſo are converted, &amp; ſo are ſaved. Mat. 13. 16. And bleſſed are all (not ſome but all) beleeuers, becauſe they all <hi>behold as in a myrror the glory of God with open face, &amp; are changed into the ſame image from glory to glory, as by the spirit of God.</hi> 2. Cor. 3 18. Neither doth our wiſe Chriſtian faith bring onely ſight and light to all that beleeue, but alſo a behauiour fit for men, indued with ſound and right reaſon, and de liuereth them from childiſhneſſe, &amp; brutiſhneſſe alſo. It is the propertie of a child to doe childiſhly. <hi>When I was a child</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>I ſpake as a child, I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood as a child: but when I was a man, I put away chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhneſſe.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Non qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſed quo itur.</note> 1. Cor. 13. 11. So it is a propertie of a brute beaſt to goe not whether they ſhould goe, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther others goe. But the faithfull ſhould not be <hi>children
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18948:14"/> in vnderſtanding,</hi> but of a ripe age. 1. Cor. 14. 20. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould they <hi>bee like the horſe and mule, in whom there is no vnderſtanding,</hi> Pſ. 32. 9. For children are chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh, and are led with ſuch motiues as moſt prevaile with the affections: and brute beaſts are brutiſh, and follow ſenſe: but the wiſe Chriſtian beleeuer will take eſpecially notice of ſuch inducements as ſoundly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the vnderſtanding, and are powerfull to rule &amp; direct the affections and ſenſes in a right courſe. Now by all theſe properties and effects of a true Chriſtian faith, it is evident, that whoſoever deſireth to attaine therevnto, muſt labour to vnderſtand the ſeverall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whereon the ſeverall doctrines of faith are groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that ſo he may bee enabled thereby to ſtand vpon the iuſt defence of his owne faith. Thus much is Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelfe forced to confeſſe, in that hee maketh ſanctity of doctrine, which is the wiſdome and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableneſſe thereof, to be a note of the true Church, and of the right faith profeſſed therein: &amp; vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ground taketh exception againſt our doctrine, and chargeth it to be vnreaſonable and abſurd, and ſo vnholy, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not the doctrine of the true Church, and of the right faith profeſſed therein. For the proofe whereof he giueth inſtance in fiue points. And firſt he beginneth with iuſtification by faith: and againſt the truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, maketh this weake and childiſh Sophiſme. If faith (ſaith he) iuſtifieth and aſſureth the faithful of his iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, then either it findeth him iuſt before he belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, or maketh him iuſt after he beleeueth. But this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion is inſufficient, and ſhould be made in this maner. If faith iuſtifieth either it is before, or when, or after it is giuen. But faith iuſtifieth both when, and after it is given, and doth never find any man iuſt before he hath obtained a right faith. And ſo the Apoſtle teacheth. Rom. 8. 30. <hi>Whom he predeſtinated</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>them be called</hi> (viz. effectually by giuing to them a true
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18948:15"/> faith) and <hi>whom he called them he iuſtified.</hi> (viz. at that preſent inſtant of time) For ſaith doth preſently ingraff the beleeuer into Chriſt, &amp; ſo giueth him preſent inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in his ſufferings and righteouſneſſe, and there by doth preſently iuſtifie him. Wherefore in this firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, reaſon faileth in this ſophiſticall confuter, and not in the doctrine which he would confute. His ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d inſtance is this: If faith giueth aſſurance of the pardon of ſinne, then it ſuffereth him not to ſay that petition of the Lords Prayer, <hi>forgiue vs our ſinnes:</hi> ſeeing it is an abſurd thing to pray for that whereof he hath good aſſurance, that he hath it already. But God giueth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes, but to ſuch as in their dayly pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers make confeſſion of them vnto him, and faithfully pray for the forgiueneſſe of them. <hi>I ſaid</hi> (ſaith David Pſ. 32. 6.) <hi>I will confeſſe againſt my ſelfe my wickedneſſe vnto the Lord, and thou forgaueſt the iniquitie of my ſin. Therefore ſhall every one that is godly make his prayer vn to thee in the time when thou maiſt be found.</hi> That is; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God is ſound of all them that ſeeke him in truth, &amp; granteth mercy and pardon of ſinne to all that humbly and faithfully ſeeke for pardon in Chriſt: Therefore every one that is godly, will in his daily prayers ſue &amp; ſeeke for the forgiueneſſe of his ſinnes in Chriſt, that ſo he may obtaine the aſſurance thereof. What? Had not that man aſſurance of the pardon of his ſinnes, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt ſaid, <hi>man thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee</hi> Luk. 5. 20. And did this man abſurdly, if he ſaid the Lords praier? Had not the Apoſtles themſelues aſſurance of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of their owne ſinnes, which were to preach and to proclaime the pardon of all ſinnes to all beleeuers? And did they ceaſe to pray, yea to pray after that manner as Chriſt commanded them to pray, <hi>forgiue vs our ſinnes?</hi> Matt. 9. 9. What doth the holy father the Pope, who in his plenary pardons, and indulgences, or all his Friers and Prieſts, who in the ſacrament of penance, giue aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18948:15"/> of the pardon of all ſinnes to ſuch as confeſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; are contrite and ſorrowfull for them, doe they I ſay forbid the ſaying of the Lords prayer, and the asking therein of the pardon of their ſinnes? Surely the holy Father himſelfe, and all the principall perſons of his Church, are abſurd men or elſe it is no abſurditie to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the faithfull of the full forgiuenes of all their ſins, and yet to will them to pray daily for the ſame. The Cardinals third inſtance is: the Anabaptiſts hold faith to be an aſſurance of Gods loue, who yet can haue no aſſurance thereof: therefore ſaith is not the aſſurance of Gods loue. As if heretikes and reprobates might not hold ſome right opinions in matters of faith. But the Anabaptiſts ſay that they themſelues haue an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Gods loue, and are accepted of him. And what of that? Did not the Laodiceans ſay that they were <hi>rich and increaſed with goods, and wanted nothing?</hi> Ap. 3. 17. And yet it was nothing ſo. So ſome mad men will ſay that they are Lords of ſuch and ſuch Mannours, vea Soveraignes of ſuch and ſuch kingdomes: and yet they may be ſtrake beggars. Now the Anabaptiſts, as all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heretikes are after a ſort mad men, and baue loſt a ſound mind: and therefore they may thinke that they haue faith and the aſſurance of Gods loue, when they haue it not indeed. The evidences wherein divers men doe ſeeke for the aſſurance of Gods loue are diverſe. The Phariſes had ſuch an high conceit of their owne workes, that they did thinke themſelues iuſt thereby, and accepted with God, as being ſuch in their owne proud opinions as did demerit no leſſe at Gods hand. So many that haue intended the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er overthrowe of Prince and people, hauing receaued abſolution from their Prieſts, and a pardon from the Pope, haue iudged themſelues to haue had all their ſinnes pardoned, and themſelues greatly beloued of God. So the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts deeming and dreaming their owne fancies to bee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18948:16"/> the immediate revelations of the ſpirit of God may happely preſume hereof, that they are right deare vnto God, and ſuch as may bee fully perſwaded of his loue. But the faithfull to whom God by his word and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, doth ſo reveale his covenant of mercy in Chriſt Ieſus, that thereby they are effectually called and brought vnto God, to truſt in this his vnſpeakable goodneſſe, and to place their chiefe happineſſe therein and to loue God for the ſame aboue all things whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; here by are rightly aſſured that they are in Gods loue, and are effectually called to the eſtate of grace, &amp; to obtaine ſalvation in Chriſt Ieſus. Wherefore albeit the aſſurance of the Anabaptiſts, and of all other of the like ranke may be falſe and vaine, for that it is built vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſandy falſe ground: yet the aſſurance of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is moſt firme and certaine, for that it is founded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a rocke. Fourthly, Bellarmine chargeth Luther with an abſurd poſition for that he avoucheth, that children being baptiſed may haue faith. Why, doth not our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour himſelfe teſtifie, that ſome at the firſt houre of the day of their life are called to worke in the Lords vineyard? Mat. 20. 1. and therefore indued with a ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified faith, which worketh by loue. And doth not the Scripture alſo in plaine words, and not in parables, teach that ſome are ſanctified fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their mothers womb, and therefore not only indued with an holy faith, but alſo with all other graces of ſanctification? Ier. 1. 5. Why doth not Bellarmine himſelfe thinke that infants deſcending from faithfull parents being baptiſed, and dying before they come to yeares of diſcreation, are Gods children and heires of his kingdome? Now how are they Gods children, vnleſſe they are reformed to his image in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe, &amp; there fore indued with a true faith which is a principall part of true holineſſe, and the very root whereout all other graces ſprout and growe? Wherefore it is no abſurdity
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18948:16"/> to thinke that children may be indued with a ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith, albeit they cannot produce the actions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, no more then it is an abſurditie to ſay that they are indued with a reaſonable ſoule, albeit the effects there of appeare not in them. But Bellarmine himſelfe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily doubting of the abſurditie of theſe former doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, in the laſt inſtance wil be ſure to produce an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd poſition indeed: which is, that God is the author of ſinne: which yet as he affirmeth is taught by Calvin. But this is an impudent and a ſhameleſſe ſlander refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and refuted alſo by that worthie ſeruant of God himſelfe. Wherefore Bellarmine hereby manifeſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth that the doctrine of the Romiſh church where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is ſo ſtiffe a maintainer, is abſurd, falſe, &amp; vntrue: &amp; therefore not taken out of the word of truth, ſeeing it is not, neither indeed cannot bee defended but by falſe ſlanders and lies. For the law of God ſhall bee ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled without lies: ſeeing wiſdome is ſufficient to a faithfull mouth, Eccl. 34. 8. And verily that all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular doctrines of the Church of Rome are vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and abſurd, and therefore vntrue by Bellarmines owne rule, vntrue it may be iuſtified in them all: but at this time I will giue inſtance only in ſome of their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular doctrines which concerne the word of God, the Sacraments, Prayer, &amp; Faith. And firſt concerning the word of God, the Church of Rome abſurdly teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that it is delivered vnto vs partly in the Scriptures, and partly by tradition. For if it bee an abſurd thing for a wiſe and provident Father to deliuer his laſt will and teſtament partly in writing and partly without: it is much more abſurd to aſcribe any ſuch action vnto the moſt wiſe and provident God. Secondly, if it be an abſurd thing for a father to interdict any of his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to get a coppie of his laſt will and teſtament, wherein ſome great legacy is giuen vnto him, and ſome ſpeciall duties are required at his hands: then it is more abſurd
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18948:17"/> to avouch that God doth interdict all his children of the Laitie, the hauing of the bookes of the old &amp; new Teſtament in the which ſo great legacies are bequea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed vnto them, and ſo many ſpeciall duties are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at their hands. Thirdly, if it be an abſurd thing that a wiſe and louing father ſhould make his laſt will and teſtament in a language vnknown to his children, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he maketh it to this end, even to make knowne to all and every of them what portion and legacie hee beſtoweth vpon them, and what dutie hee requireth at their hands; then much more abſurd is it to avouch that our heavenly father, making his wil and teſtament to the ſame end, would haue the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding thereof kept cloſe from any of his children vnder the locke &amp; key of a ſtrange language. Fourthly, ſeeing every wiſe father hath a ſpeciall care to ſet downe his mind in his will and teſtament in plaine and cleere words, that ſo he may take away all iuſt occaſion of diſcord and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention among his children: it is abſurd to imagine that the God of peace and loue would ſet downe his mind in the bookes of the old and new Teſtament in darke and obſcure tearmes, and in phraſes of ſuch a doubtfull and ambiguous ſignification that like a noſe of wax they may be bowed as wel this way as that way, and ſo miniſter occaſion of diſcord and ſtrife which he therein ſo ſtraightly and ſeverely interdicteth? And verily as it is an abſurd thing to avouch that the light of the ſunne is darke, becauſe ſore eies cannot well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it, &amp; blind cannot apprehend it at al: ſo is it more abſurd to avouch that the holy Scripture being a light that proceedeth from Chriſt the ſonne of righteouſnes Ap. 12. 1. is darke and obſcure, becauſe the ſore eyes of ſome mens ſicke minds are offended with it, and the blind mindes of other that are ſtarke dead in their ſins cannot apprehend it at all. Fiftly, ſeeing it is an abſurd thing to thinke that any perſon in a manuary craft can
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18948:17"/> become a good Artiſan, vnleſſe he vnderſtand the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular rules thereof, and the reaſons of ſuch workes that are to be wrought thereby: it is no leſſe abſurd to determine with the Church of Rome, that a blind and a colliar-like faith can make a true faithfull man, and a good intent can make a good worke, when the party vnderſtandeth not the particular doctrines of faith, nor the ſeverall reaſons whereby a good worke may bee done rightly &amp; acceptably vnto God. For is it not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd (as Chryſoſtome ſaith) that a Phyſitian, a Tanner, a Cloth-worker, and all other craftſinen ſhall be able to ſtand in defence of their arts: and a Chriſtian ſhall not be able to giue a reaſon of his faith? Whereas theſe arts neglected bring loſſe only to our temporalties: &amp; the contempt of the other bringeth damage to our ſoules. Yet (ſaith he) ſuch is our madneſſe that wee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy all our thoughts vpon the former, and little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the neceſſary &amp; moſt ſtrong fortifications of our ſalvation: albeit wee bee commanded to bee ready to giue an anſwer to every one that ſhould aske vs a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our faith, &amp; alſo to haue the word of God dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in vs moſt plentifully. Chryf. hom. 16. in Ioh. Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if we thinke it abſurd to truſt another mans telling in the receipt of mony, or another mans eie in the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of our horſe, or another mans taſt in the food of our owne bodies: It is more abſurd to receaue from our teachers the heauenly coine of faith, hope, &amp; loue, vpon their bare word, or to truſt his eies and taſt in the food of our ſoules by receauing and approuing all do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines deliuered by them vnto vs without all examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and triall. So S. Chryſoſtome. It is an abſurd thing in the receipt of mony, not to truſt another, but to tell it our ſelues: and in matters of farre greater moment to content our ſelues with another mans bare word: eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially whereas we haue a moſt exact ballance, ſquire, and rule, even the determination of the divine lawes.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18948:18"/> Chryf. hom. 13. in 2. ep. ad Cor. Laſtly, is it not moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd that a tranſlation made by ſome which were not inſpired &amp; guided therein by the ſpirit of God, ſhould be commanded to be receaued by all, as only authenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, &amp; to be preferred before the text it ſelfe ſet down in the bookes of the Canonicall Scripture, penned in the Hebrew &amp; Greek tongues by the Prophets &amp; Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, which were immediatly inſpired and guided in that very action by the ſpeciall motion of the vnerring ſpirit of God? 2. Pet. 1. 20. 21. Is it not, I ſay, abſurd that all truth moſt purely ſet downe by ſuch notaries as were immediately thereto deſigned by God, ſhould not be ſo well preſerued in their regiſter bookes from all errors and corruptions by divine providence, as in the writings of any other which were not immediatly by God deſigned therevnto? For is water more cleere in the ſtreame where it may gather mud, then in the <note place="margin">Dulcius ex ipſo fente bibuntur aqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> moſt pure fountaine it ſelfe? <hi>Hence ſpring errors</hi> (ſaith S. Cyprian) <hi>while men repaire not to the originall veritie nor the head is ſought after, nor the doctrine of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly maſter is obſerved.</hi> Cyp. de ſimpl. praelat. Sccondly to come to the doctrines of the Church of Rome, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Sacraments: Is it not abſurd that the bare pronouncing of a few words ſhould conſecrate a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and that a Sacrament ſhould giue grace by the worke wrought; albeit the words themſelues bee not vnderſtood, nor the vſes and ends, for the which Sacraments were ordained? <hi>Tell mee</hi> (ſaith S. Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome) <hi>O thou fooliſh, or abſurd Prieſt, doth the vertue of the word of God conſiſt in the forme of the letters, or in the vnderſtanding of the ſenſe?</hi> Chryſ. hom. 43. in Mat. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily the Apoſtle teacheth, that <hi>the word of God profiteth not vnleſſe it be mingled with faith in them that heare it.</hi> Heb. 4. 2. that is, vnleſſe it be ſo deliuered that the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers minds may be inſtructed and edified thereby, and ſo faith may be either begotten, or at leaſt ſtrengthned
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18948:18"/> in them. And ſo doth S. Auſtine teach, both concerning the word and the Sacraments alſo. From whence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth this power (ſaith hee) that water doth touch the body &amp; cleanſe the ſoule, but by meanes of the word, and that not becauſe it is vttered, but becauſe it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued. For in the word the vaniſhing ſound is one thing, and the remaining power another. This is the word of faith which we preach. Aug. in Ioh. hom. 80. And againe, <hi>The faith of the Sacraments doe iuſtifie, not</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Fides Sacra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum iuſtiſicat non ſacraments.</note> 
               <hi>the Sacraments themſelues.</hi> And therefore (ſaith hee) <hi>in the Sacraments wee muſt not regard what they are, but what they ſignifie.</hi> Aug. cont. Max. l. 3. cap. 22. For as in the Iewiſh ſacrifices, ſo in theſe our Chriſtians Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>God doth not require the worke wrought, but the reaſons and ends for the which it is wrought.</hi> Tertull. l. 3. cont. Marc. Secondly, it is not abſurd that a Sacrament which of the very worke wrought (as they ſay) giveth grace, ſhould hinder grace giuen in another ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as they affirme of marriage, and of their holy orders? As if one grace could diſgrace another: or one inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Subordinata <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pugnant.</note> ordained to giue grace could reſiſt the efficacie, and power of another. Thirdly, was not their ancient order of baptiſing of Bels, an abſurd diſorder? As if Chriſt had ſhed his blood for the purging of the ſinnes of Bells, &amp; had ordained baptiſme to giue to them his heavenly grace: But to leaue baptiſme, and to come to the Lords ſupper. what a Chaos of abſurdities doe they bring in about the ſame? Firſt, whereas the Scripture in plaine words avoucheth that our bleſſed Saviour at the firſt inſtitution thereof, tooke bread and wine in their eſſence and ſubſtance to make them the myſticall ſignes of his body and bloud, they ſay that he tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiated them into the very ſubſtance of his body &amp; blood, &amp; left their accidences only to be the outward ſignes in the ſacrament. Whereas, <hi>Sacraments if they had not acertaine reſemblance with the things whereof
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18948:19"/> they are Sacraments, they could not be ſacraments at all, and beare the name of the things themſelues which</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exijſdem nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; ſumu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. ex ijſdem naſcimur &amp; paſcimur. Bern. Accidens non tranſit à ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>biecto in ſubiectum. Accidentis eſſe eſt ineſſe.</note> 
               <hi>they reſemble,</hi> Aug. ad Bonif. ep. 23. Now what reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance can there bee betweene the accidents of bread and wine, and the true and reall body and bloud of Chriſt? Can theſe accidents nouriſh our bodies, that they may reſemble the nouriſhment of our ſoules by the body and bloud of Chriſt? And is it not abſurd that theſe accidents being ſeparated from their ſubiects muſt not onely retaine their being, but alſo ſubſiſt by themſelues? Surely it were fit that theſe mens bodies were fed with accidents, which feed mens ſoules with ſuch abſurd fancies. Now concerning Chriſts body &amp; blood which is the inward grace in this ſacrament, how many abſurdities alſo doe they avouch? Firſt they will haue the very ſame body and blood daily to bee made of the ſubſtance of bread and wine through the pronunciation of fiue words by the mouth of a Prieſt, which was but once made of the ſubſtance of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mary by the operation of the holy Ghoſt. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they will haue it ſtill here in earth which is aſcended vp into heaven. Yea they will haue it here to bee daily eaten with our bodily mouthes, which is not onely an abſurd and an inhumane impietie in the iudgement of S. Auſtine de doct. chriſt. l. 3. c. 10. but hath been an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to Inſidels to condemne Chriſtians for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedſt monſters that were in all the whole world, for that they were not aſhamed to ſay that they daily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured their Lord and God. Thirdly, they teach that the body of Chriſt which is a true naturall body, is in their maſſe vncircumſcribed without any dimenſions, and the ſame in heauen circumſcribed and hauing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions. Laſtly, they teach that Chriſts body here is not limited in ſpace or place, but that it is ſo in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and therefore is in heauen a true body, but not here in earth. For (as Auſtine ſaith) <hi>take away from a body ſpace
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18948:19"/> or place, and it ſhall be no where, or in no place, and if it bee no where it is not at all.</hi> But all theſe abſurdities they thinke they may cure with this ſalue; for that all theſe things are and may bee ſtill done by the miraculous hand and power of God. But Auſtine refuſeth this plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter as not fit for this ſore. For (as hee teacheth) <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may haue honour as being religious: but they doe not worke astoniſhment as being miraculous.</hi> For they are ſuch meanes as God hath appointed to confirme the faith of ſuch as already beleeue; and not to convert vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuers, for the which end miracles are ordained. 1. Cor. 14 22. And verily if theſe workes were miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, they ſhould be ſuch as might be firſt apprehended by ſenſe, that from thence they might enter into the conſcience. But theſe which they call miraculous works, are not apprehended by ſenſe, as ſenſe it ſelfe doth teſtifie ſufficiently. Thirdly, concerning prayer: Firſt, is it not abſurd that publike prayers vnto which a publike aſſent ſhould be giuen by the people, ſhould be made in a tongue not vnderſtood of the people. For (For (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>VVhen thou bleſſeſt with the ſpirit,</hi> (viz. in a tongue vnknowne) <hi>how ſhall he that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupieth the roome of the vnlearned ſay amen at thy giuing of thankes, ſeeing hee knoweth not what thou ſaiſt</hi> 1. Cor. 14. 16. Secondly, is it not abſurd that private prayers ſhould bee commanded to bee made in a tongue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to him that maketh them, and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not vnderſtand for what he himſelfe prayeth? For ſhould any one preſent a ſupplication to a Prince, and not vnderſtand what is contained in his ſupplication? much leſſe ſhould he doe it to the king of kings, vnleſſe he looke to be re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ected as a fooliſh and an abſurd com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, yea as a frantike &amp; mad man. Thirdly, is it not abſurd to pray to Saints for ſuch bleſſings as cannot be giuen but by God alone? ſeeing it is all one, as if one ſhould ſeeke for that of a ſubiect, which is only in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18948:20"/> hands of a king to giue. Fourthly, were it not abſurd, when thou haſt the kings eldeſt and deareſt ſonne to be thy mediator to his father, to requeſt ſome meane perſons of the court to be thy mediators alſo, as if the mediation of ſuch a perſon were not ſufficient? So is it farre more abſurd to ioine the Saints to the Sonne of God in the wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of mediation, whereas his interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with the father is 10000000000 times more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected of God, then is the interceſſion of all Angells and Saints. Laſtly, is it not abſurd to make the Saints mediators to Chriſt, when be himſelfe calleth thee, &amp; promiſeth to heare and helpe thee alſo, whenſoever thou by thy ſelfe ſhalt come vnto him in faithfull and humble prayer? Mat. 11. 28. For hee loueth his faithfull ſervants better then any creature can loue him: and therefore they ought to come rather to him then to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other. I come with more comfort (ſaid an ancient autor) to my Ieſus then to any of the Saints. For this cannot be the ſaying of S. Auſtine, becauſe he renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth <note place="margin">Dulcius ad me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Ieſum acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do quam ad que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis ſanctorum.</note> all other mediators but Chriſt: and ſaith more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that, <hi>if S. Iohn himſelfe ſhould take vpon him to bee our Mediator, he ſhould ſhew himſelfe thereby to be a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Antechriſt.</hi> Aug. cont. ep. Parm. l. 2. c. 8. Laſt of all, concerning faith they teach moſt abſurdly of all other. For where as our commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Creed containing the ſumm of our Chriſtian faith, teacheth vs to beleeue in God, that is, to be fully perſwaded that God is our God and louing father in Chriſt, and hath taken vs for his adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted children even all and every one of vs, vnto whome he hath giuen a true faith: how can this faith taught in our common Creed ſtand with that of the church of Rome, which commandeth vs ſtill to ſtand in doubt of Gods loue? Why? is not Gods loue towards his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and obedient children, greater then is the loue of any earthly father to his? And would not an earthly Father who hath declared his great loue toward his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18948:20"/> louing child in giuing him the beſt education that hee can, and the greateſt portion &amp; the largeſt inheritance take it very vnkindly at his childs hand, if for all this he ſhould make but the leaſt doubt of his ſo entire and tender affection and loue? Now our heauenly father giueth to all that are adopted ſonnes by faith in Chriſt a farre better education, greater portion and larger in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance then all earthly parents can giue, and that to this end to teſtifie vnto them the vnſearchable riches of his goodneſſe towards them, and to giue them full aſſurance of his vnſpeakable loue. And yet ſhall they be commanded ſtill to make doubt thereof? yea where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as all profeſſions in the whole world bee they heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, Iewiſh, Haereticall or ſchiſmaticall doe make ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne proteſtation that they will giue aſſurance, albeit vpon moſt falſe and deceauable grounds, to their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and followers, that if they will rightly embrace their rules and put in practiſe their commandements, they ſhall thereby be brought neare vnto God, &amp; haue aſſurance of his favour and loue? And ſhall our chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an profeſſion, which only delivereth the true grounds of our reconciliation and peace with God, and of his good will and loue towards the faithfull, even by the teſtimonies of a multitude of heavenly Angels, Luk. 2. 14. yet be counter commanded herein, &amp; that by that Church which vaunteth her ſelfe to bee the only pillar and rocke of faith? Vndoubtedly as that perſon is no chaſt wife, nor true mother, that willeth the children ſtill to ſtand in doubt of the kindneſſe of their carefull and louing father: ſo the church of Rome hereby ſhew eth her ſelfe neither to bee the chaſt ſpouſe of Chriſt, nor the naturall mother of the faithfull, but the whore of Babylon, &amp; the mother of all abominations, in that ſhee commandeth the faithfull which are the children of God ſtill to ſtand in doubt of the loue of God their heauenly father. Wherefore to conclude, as on the one
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18948:21"/> ſide we are to pray vnto God our heavenly father that he would ſtill deliuer vs from the wicked doctrines of evill and vnreaſonable Papiſts, becauſe they be not the doctrines of faith and truth: ſo we are on the other ſide ſtill to pray vnto him, that he would cauſe the doctrine of the Goſpell to be publiſhed more and more, that he would giue it a full current, and cauſe it to be glorified throughout the whole earth. And let vs alſo pray that the Lord our God by the miniſterie of one Haggei or other would lay open the ends and vſes of ſuch gentle corrections, which of late yeares our land hath bin vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited withal againe and againe, &amp; ſtirre vp the ſpirits of our Zorobabels and Ioſhuahs to haue a care, firſt to build the temple of the Lord before the care of build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their own houſes. And that our wiſe Solomon would not only haue a care, firſt to build the temple of God before the building of his owne pallace, but alſo haue a greater care for the one then for the other: that ſo of him it might be truely ſaid: Behold a greater then Solomon is here. Yea that God would more and more ſettle in the heart of our David King <hi>Iames</hi> this ſerious meditation, which ſo throughly poſſeſſed the ſoule of king David: Behold, I dwel in an houſe of Cedar trees, and the arke of the Lord in divers places of my king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome dwelleth vnder curtaines by the want of skilfull builders to build it a Temple: that ſo not only our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans may ſay vnto our King: Goe &amp; doe all that is in thine heart: for God is with thee: but alſo his God may ſay vnto him: haſt thou ſuch a care to build an houſe vnto me? Behold, in lue there of, thine houſe ſhall bee eſtabliſhed and thy kingdome before thee for ever, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thy throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed for ever, 2. Sam 7. 16. even ſo oh faithfull, Amen; ſay Amen, and confirme this thine owne decree, that it may be as the decrees of the Medes and Perſians that cannot bee altered. And ſay againe and againe of our King <hi>Iames,</hi> and his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18948:21"/> as thou didſt once of David &amp; his Sion. I haue choſen great Brittaine, and loued to dwel in it, ſaying: This is my reſt for ever, here will I dwell, for I haue a delight therein. I will bleſſe her victuals with increaſe, &amp; ſatisfie her poore with bread. I will cloth her Prieſts with health, and her Saints ſhall reioice and ſing. Here will I make the horne of <hi>Iames</hi> to flouriſh: I haue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained a lanthorne for mine annointed. And as for his enimies I will cloath them with ſhame: but vpon his head ſhall the crowne flouriſh. Pſ. 132. And let every faithfull Britaine crie out to his companion in faith &amp; country ſaying. O pray for the peace of London, they ſhall proſper that loue thee. Peace be within thy wals, and plentie within thy pallaces. For my bretheren and companions ſake I will wiſh thee now proſperitie: yea becauſe of the houſe of the Lord our God I will ſeeke to doe thee good. Pſ. 122. Laſtly, to conclude, let every faithfull ſoule whereſoever after this or the like maner commend his owne ſoule and ſalvation into the hands of his redeemer. <hi>Into thy hands Lord I commend my spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which is thy due: for why thou haſt redeemed it O Lord my God moſt true. Send out thy light, that is, thy truth, and lead me with thy grace: which may conduct mee to thine hill and to thy dwelling place. One thing of thee I doe require that thou wilt not deny: for which I pray and will deſire till thou to me apply. That I within his holy place my life throughout may dwell: to ſee the beauty of thy face, and view thy Temple well. The greater ſort craue worldly goods, and riches doe imbrace: but Lord grant mee thy countenance thy favour and thy grace. For thou thereby ſhalt make mine heart more ioyfull and more glad, then they that of their corne and wine full great increaſe haue had. In peace therefore lye downe will I, taking my reſt &amp; ſleepe: for thou only wilt me O Lord alone in ſafetie keepe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:18948:22"/>
            <p>The grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and the loue of God, and the fellowſhip of the holy Ghoſt bee with vs all. Amen. Yea thou that art God to be bleſſed for ever ſo in grace vouchſafe to be with vs that thou bleſſe the continuall miniſterie of thine holy word and heavenly Angels to our continuall ſanctification and preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this life, and to our full and finall glorification in the life to come.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18948:22"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18948:23"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18948:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18948:24"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18948:24"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18948:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18948:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:18948:26"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:18948:26"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:18948:27"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18948:27"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:18948:28"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:18948:28"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
